the best things we can do for bone
health are the following get it as good
as you possibly can as a kid
particularly during those three to four
years during puberty I said that earlier
but I will probably I would like to say
it 50 more times before we're done today
that's how critical this stuff is we're
really talking about nutrition but
especially talking about movement
exercise physical activity whatever
phrase you want to give it you got to
move as a kid you got to move during
puberty what do we know about exercise
after this puberty right so now we're
generally thinking I've gotten into my
20s 30s or more and I'm now I got low
bone density how do I get it back up
what do we know well exercise studies
still work the magnitude of effect is
smaller to be totally honest it's
generally still statistically
significant and clinically meaningful
but the numbers you're going to see
there are somewhere between like 3 to
2% which is again crazy if I told you
this six months intervention gave you a
half a percent increase in strength
you'd be like that sucked but a half a
perc increase in bone is like yay that
that's great we're super happy there
right while the bone Minal density
effect is smaller you start to add on
other things right think about all the
countless benefits of exercise that
you're getting from any other variable
but in this thing you start now getting
balance and you start getting a
reduction in Falls so there is a
significant reduction in your likel of
having a fall when you exercise you're
not going to break your bone if you
don't fall and so you're kind of
actually keeping your bones healthier
from two sides of the equation now the
bone itself as well as reducing the
likel of putting your bone in a bad
position it is very very clear hopefully
I made this argument that just being
physically active as a kid is is enough
you can get there you don't have to lift
weights you don't have to play sports if
you're active enough you're jumping and
playing and doing things like that as a
kid you're probably fine as an adult
though it's not the same story
unfortunately almost surely at this
point you're going to have to go out of
your way to strength train as an adult
let's start off by remembering the
mechanism Wolf's Law stress is we're all
about stress here causing
adaptation where we get thrown off here
is it's not the actual load that matters
it is the change in load so if you are
not used to lifting weights at all if
you never run if you don't do anything
that puts a huge impact on your bone if
you get a little impact on your bone
that's enough to stimulate growth
however if you're already at a
reasonable amount of loading you have to
do more than you've currently been doing
to stimulate bone growth it is the
change it is the altering from
homeostasis that signals it not the
actual load itself and this part is
critical because what it emphasizes is
progression we have to do certain types
of of exercises in amounts and
progression strategies that continue to
challenge it which means it needs to
continue to be overloaded to continue to
remodel and add additional bone density
those osteocytes that we talked about
earlier the blasts and the class get
desensitized really quickly to the same
stimuli it's very very adaptable I said
earlier in the show that we tend to
think about bone is this kind of this
inert thing and it's not it's highly
highly plastic and it is paying
attention this desensitization happens
really quickly this is why things like
static loads and repetitive kind of low
magnitude loads are not osteogenic
Unfortunately they are great for lots of
things they're
awesome but for bone mineral density
bone health specifically they're just
not very effective if effective at all
you have to emphasize rather impact
dependent things so you can impact the
ground this is landing jumping up and
down and Landing you could do tumbling
like I guess you could join a judo class
or a Jitsu or gymnastics something where
you're landing and the impact is
happening all over the place the most
common and and where a lot of the
research got started here was actually
in tennis players so there some of the
original research on this entire
understanding of the role of impact on
bone moral density came from studies in
which they looked and they realized that
you know tennis players had way more
bone Minal density in the arm that they
hold their racket in and so you think
like really that tiny little tennis ball
that weighs a few
ounces well that was enough why because
it was happening rapidly right smashing
full
velocity that led to the significantly
different B we see this all the time in
our pitchers and and different athletes
that have sort of asymmetrical loading
strategies so the ground can be
something that you impact it could be an
Implement again like a tennis racket it
could be simp simply faster pulling on
the bone so you're doing any exercise or
activity and it's requiring you to snap
and Pull and change directions or
whatever the case is as long as that's
being done aggressively then those
osteocytes are going to feel like
literally feel that on the bone and then
start adding to that Reformation or that
bone metabolism process so now that you
understand the concepts we're trying to
get after I thought it'd be helpful to
go over one very specific protocol what
I'm going to get into is What's called
the lift more randomized control trials
this was all by Belinda Beck who's a GF
Coast in Australia I think but the lift
more is l f m o r I love when scientists
come up with awesome names for their
control trials U these originally came
out in like 2017 2018 and I'm I'm not
going to exaggerate here by calling
these groundbreaking and that's because
I remember still as an undergraduate
graduate student being terrified
honestly of working with anybody older
because of Frailty concerns and that's
because people would just Hammer you
they would really put the fear of of
Zeus in you that you're going to break
somebody's bones and so we were
terrified of having people lift weights
if they were unless we knew for a fact
that they had quality bones prior to
2017 we had really very little evidence
that strength training was okay and safe
for people with osteoporosis and we had
very little evidence that was actually
beneficial until these lift more control
trials started coming out these lift
trials there was a bunch of them but the
one I'm going to focus on right now was
I think the first one and it was in
postmenopausal women that had known low
bone mass right so they knew these women
were at risk they later repeated it in
men now the trial itself was 8 months
long and what they did is they looked at
a uh what they called like a higher
intensity resistance and impact training
and they compared that to lower impact
training the higher impact training was
twice per week for 30
minutes and it was supervised I think it
was in the clinic okay and what they did
is they did five sets of five
repetitions at 85% of one rep max right
which is awesome you would generally
think what like you're when we think
exercise in in clinical populations
we're always like you know three sets of
10 at 60% kind of thing they said no
we're taking people that we know we're
at you know higher risk of fractures and
Falls we're doing 5x5 at
85% four exercises I think they did
deadlift back squat um overhead press
and then the impact came with this
jumping chin up exercise so the people
stood kind of below the bar they jumped
up grabbed the chin up bar did a pullup
or a chin up and then all the way at the
top let go fell all the way back down to
the ground and landed so they were
getting that plyometric uh emphasis by
by Landing there so those four exercises
took about 30 minutes the other group
did lower and intensity stuff like
walking uh lunges they did front raises
and some other body weight exercises and
I think the highest they let them get up
to was 3 kilograms of load so they did
it at home they did low air intensity
stuff now there had been enough studies
done at this point that you basically
knew the lower intensity was not going
to work like we just simply know walking
doesn't do the trick for bone maral
density um three kilograms is not going
to be
enough and then to kind of summarize
what found out was the the higher
intensity
resistance impact training stuff it
basically won there was a lot of
measures taken there was a lot of bone
mle density measures taken and again
basically all the metrics at I'm
exaggerating a little bit but most of
the metrics for bone Minal density
improved way more in the lifting and
Landing group than the low intensity
group strength got better so this was
really impactful because it answered two
really big questions arguably three one
you're not going to break people they if
done properly and supervised and there's
more detail to how they they warm people
up and like all that stuff's in the
paper right 5x5 85% four big exercises
and these people didn't break bones
which in of itself was enough to to
shock many people number two it actually
was way more effective than the standard
exercise programs the third one I would
argue is this translated into other
things in life because their legs got
stronger their upand go time their uh
sit to stand times these functional
activities of daily living metrics got
way better as well so translated into
other areas of their life which is
impactful
so since then it's been very hard to
argue
scientifically that lifting weights is
is dangerous or something you should
avoid for people with osteoporosis in
fact I think we can say pretty
definitively this point it's a very very
good thing to do so if you're the type
of person who likes to listening to
podcast like this and want an exact
number an exact routine you can go
follow the protocol that Belinda did in
her studies if you like things more
broadly if I were to summarize the whole
field this is what I'd say the bone
health exercise guidelines look like
this is everything from how frequent how
intense what exercises rest volume and
so on and so forth so starting us off
with intensity one thing that we know
has to happen is the intensity of
exercise has to be somewhere between
moderate to high that directly
influences our exercise choice
the exercises have to be
weightbearing you generally want them to
be
multi-directional because the
adaptations are sight specific in other
words if you do nothing but upper body
Plyometrics so imagine doing like a
push-up and Landing with the pushup
you're not going to see any change in
your lumbar or your femur or your hips
in terms of boneal density the same is
true with the opposite if all you're
doing is Plyometrics your upper body
won't change its Bal density
it is site specific that is really clear
from the research so you want to do
multi-directional total body different
movement patterns frontal pattern
frontal plane sagittal plane uh
rotational movements like all kinds of
things like this right to get all
aspects of bone manal density high so we
got to be intense we got to load it and
we want to pick exercises uh that are
well-rounded in terms of how I'm getting
loaded and in the areas that I'm loading
it if you do that
then all you want to do is try to get as
much stimuli on there as as you can
what's that mean
frequency can you give me two days a
week great can you give me four better
can you give me seven even better now
that's not the case for things like
muscle growth right but we're not trying
to do that right now if you want the
most amount of stimuli on the the bone
then stimulate at the most amount that
you possibly can so the more frequent
the better in terms of challenging the
bomb if you do those three things then
when it comes to volume and rest and
order you can do really whatever you
want as long as it doesn't compromise
the previous ones so here's what I mean
if you want to do a set of 50
repetitions and you want to take a 20
second break and do it again and your
heart rate gets really really high and
you get a lot of sweat going on is that
going to help bone moral
density probably not because what had to
happen with load you had to go light for
that right because you did a lot of reps
and you get to high fatigue and so you
probably didn't get enough impacts to
stimulate the muscle growth this is not
a game of fatigue we're not talking
about fat loss we're not talking about
building your endurance or your
mitochondrial health or anything else
like that we got to make sure the
intensity and the loading are there so
as long as your
volume whether this is the amount of
repetitions per set the amount of sets
you're doing the resting levels you're
taking are not taking away from the
things that have to happen then you can
really do whatever you would like here
the order of the exercises same think it
doesn't matter bone doesn't care about
order not a big deal you got to be able
to progress which is our last modifiable
variable long as you can do that
everything else is entirely up to you
modify it how you see fit always
customize always individualize but make
sure you hit those previous Concepts and
you should be doing the best you can for
using exercise to stimulate bone growth
if you enjoyed this clip you can watch
the full episode by clicking here
[Music]